Hello. And welcome back to our Image and Video
大家好 欢迎回到我们的图像与视频处理课程上来
Processing Class. We have seen very interesting effects
我们能从这些图片中得到很有趣的效果
that we can obtain in images just by doing these very, very simple local
仅通过这些十分简单的 局部邻域操作
neighborhood operations. Let's use this video to see a couple of
让我们通过这个视频来看看其它操作
additional ones. In particular, we're going to talk about
尤其是 我们将说到导数
derivatives. How we implement those derivatives with
我们如何对邻域求导数
local neighborhoods, and what important are, how important are those derivatives
重要的是 这些导数操作将让图片产生
to do very, very interesting effects in images.
非常非常有趣的效果
So let's dive into that. Here we have a picture.
让我们接下来深入探讨 这里有一幅图
It's a one dimensional image that has flat, rump, flat and a very, very sharp
这是一幅一维的图像 这里是平的 然后下降 再是平的 接着陡升
jump and flat again. And let's see what happens when we take
然后又是平直的 我们来看看在对它求导数后会变成怎样
the derivatives of this. I have drawn this here.
我将求导后的图形画在这儿
But before that you might ask yourself, derivatives, that's a continuous
在那之前你可能会问 求导应该是在连续性条件下的运算
operation. How can we implement that in our
我们怎么在电脑上进行
computer? There are many, many ways of doing that.
有很多很多种方式能够做到
But let me illustrate a very simple one. If I want to take the derivative of an
但我展示一种非常简单的 如果我想要对一幅
image, in the x direction, I can basically write that in discrete
图像在 x方向 进行求导的话 我只要用离散的形式写成
fashion as f, add the pixel x1-fx.
f(x+1) - f(x)
+ 1 - f(x). Very simple.
非常简单
I just subtract two consecutive pixels. If I want to write the neighborhood
我仅需将两个相邻的像素值相减 如果我想对邻域进行操作的话
operation. Let's say in a 3x3 that would mean f(x +
假设是一个 3x3 区域 就是说 f(x+1)
1), I have a 1 here, - f(x). I have a minus one here, and I replace as
在这儿有个1 而对应-f(x) 在这儿有个-1 我将其它的都用0替代
a zero. So that's basically how I represent that.
基本上就是这样表示的
I get, a one dimensional derivative in the x direction.
于是我就得到了 x方向 的一阶导数
Similarly, I can get a one dimensional derivative in the y direction.
类似的 我能得到 y方向的一阶导数
So we see here that, simulated values of this rump, flat, jump and flat.
我们看这儿 是这条折线的假设值
So we start with flat 6 we have a, decrease in rump,
所以从此处的 6 开始 在下降区减少
flat 1 and then a big jump. The first derivative is this first row
然后一直是1 再是陡升 一阶导数是第一行的数
that we see here. Very easy to compute following this
用这个方法能很容易算出
operation. We have actually a couple of 0s because
我们这有几个0
there's no derivative. The values are constant.
因为这里没有导数 这些值是常数
Then basically we have a -1, -1 that means that the pixel values are
接着得到-1 -1意味着像素值
decreasing in jumps and constant jumps of one.
以恒定的跃变值1下降
It's negative, so they are decreasing. And then once again, we have flat.
它是负的 因此是下降 接下来与之前一样 是平的
And then there's a big jump here when we do 6 - 1,
然后这里有个大的跃变 我们用 (6 - 1)
we're going to get 5 and then it flattens out again.
得到5 后面又一次变平缓
So we already see that considering the first derivative, we can understand that
我们已经看到如果考虑一阶导数 我们可以理解
for example there is a rump, a smooth decline of pixel values and then
比如这是下降区 像素值平缓下降
there's a big jump. Very interesting with a derivative we can
接着是一个大的跃变 非常有趣的是 我们能通过导数
detect jumps as we expected. Then we can take actually the second
来感知跃变 然后我们实际上能够求二阶导数
derivative. And once again we can write an explicit
同样的 我们能够写一个具体的方程
formula and a mask for this second derivative.
还有模板 来表示二阶导数
So we are going to do this second derivative of our image, once again in
于是我们来求这个图像的二阶导数
the x direction. And once again there are many ways of
同样也是 x方向 也是有很多很多种方式来求
implementing the second derivative but one of them is to take f at x + 1 + f(x -
其中一种求取二阶导数的方法 就是取 f(x+1) 加上 f(x-1)
1) and subtract 2 times f at the actual pixel.
再减去2乘以此处的像素值 即 2f(x)
And that's, once again, very simple to do with our, ubiquitous 3x3.
对普通的 3x3 来说 实现起来也很简单
Now we have a -2 here. A 1 and a 1 on each one of the sides
此时在这儿为-2 两边各一个1
representing these two. And then we have a 0 everyplace else.
代表这两个数 然后其它处均为0
if we do that, so that's kind of an addition derivative
如果我们这样做 就是对一阶导数再求导
to the first derivative. It's a very simple exercise.
这是非常简单的操作
We are, have to take derivatives of these.
我们对这些进行求导
We could directly apply this to the original one if we want.
我们可以直接对最初的数值进行这种求导
But it's easier just to take, you know, continuous pixel subtraction to the next
但是这样会更简单 连续的像素中 相邻的两个相减
one. And we see jumps when there are big
当有较大变化时我们会看见跃变
changes. So, 0 - 0 is 0.
而这里 (0 - 0) 还是0
For example -1 - -1, once again, 0. But when there are changes, we see a
而这里 (-1 - (-1))时 又是0 但当这里有变化时
jump. We see 1 here.
我们会看见跃变 这儿是1
We see another here. So the second derivative very clearly
这里还有一个跃变 所以二阶导数很清楚地
marks when there are big changes in our image.
表明在我们的图像中何处有大的变化
And that's extremely powerful. We are detecting big changes by doing
这是十分有效的 我们通过求导数 来检验大的变化
derivatives which are, at least in their simplest fashion, implemented with masks
以最简单的形式 运用像这样的掩模来实现
like this one. So let's just continue with this, and see
我们继续
some of the examples in a second. Here are different masks that compute
来看一些例子 这些是不同的掩模
different types of derivatives. So I'm going to ask you, look at this
可以用于计算不同类型的导数 我想问问你们
mask, for example, and tell me what is this mask actually computing?
例如 看这个掩模 能告诉我这个实际上是计算什么吗？
Is it computing the third derivative for example in the x direction?
是用来计算 x方向的三阶导数吗？
Is it computing the third derivative in the y direction?
还是计算在 y方向的三阶导数？
Or is it computing the sum of the derivatives in the first the first
又或者是计算一阶导数
derivatives in the x and y directions? Or is it computing the sum of the second
在 x方向和y方向的和？ 或者是计算
derivatives in the x and the second derivative in the y direction.
在 x方向和 y方向的二阶导数之和呢？
An interesting property. So what is this mask implementing?
一个非常有趣的性质 那这个掩模是怎么用呢？
I thought that, that wasn't too hard for you, so I gave you that as an exercise,
我觉得它对你们而言应该不难 所以把它作为你们的练习
but I just write it down. This is actually computing the sum of the
但我只是写出来了 这实际上是计算
second derivative in the x direction and the second derivative, in the y
x方向 和 y方向的二阶导数之和
direction. So this is computing, the second
所以这是计算
derivative of f in the x direction plus the second derivative of y.
f 在x方向的二阶导数 加上 在y方向的二阶导数
Of f, I apologize, in the y direction.
对不起 是f在y方向上的二阶导数
And that's basically we know, either from the previous slide,
这大概就是我们从之前的课中所知道的
because we can compute the second derivative in x and the second derivative
因为我们能计算出 x方向和y方向的二阶导数
in y, and add them. And we actually know that that's
并且将它们相加 我们知道它实际上就是
basically f(x + 1) + f(x - 1) - 2f(x). And I am not writing the ys, because they
f(x+1) + f(x-1)-2f(x) 我就不写y方向的了 因为它们基本没变
haven't changed. It should be at y, y and y and plus.
这是y 这也是y 这个也一样 把它们加到前面
So this was x and now we are going to do y.
这是x方向的 我们现在写出y方向的
That's f(y + 1) + f(y - 1) - 2f(y). And once again, all these are for a
就是 f(y + 1) + f(y - 1) - 2f(y) 同样 这些都是对于常量x而言
constant x. So all these are for a constant y.
这些都是对于常量y而言
And all these are for a constant x. When we add them, we get this.
这些都是对于常量x而言 当我们把它们相加 我们就得到了这个
And this is actually what's called the Laplacian of f.
这实际上就被称作 f 的拉普拉斯算子
And we briefly talked about this when we were talking about the relationships
我们简要的介绍过这个 当我们谈论
between averaging and the Guassian filtering, and the heat equation.
均值处理、高斯滤波以及热方程之间的关系时
So this is what's called the Laplacian of the image,
所以这就是图像的拉普拉斯算子
is the sum of the second derivatives in the x and in the y direction.
是x方向与y方向上的二阶导数之和
These are different implementations of the laplacian.
这些是拉普拉斯算子的不同实现形式
Here for example we make the difference even stronger.
在此 我们使得变化更为明显
We stretch it. And we're going to see the effects of
我们将其加强 便能看到它的效果
that. The basic idea is that in the
基本的原理是这样
surrounding, basically we have one sign and in the pixel we have a different
周围的像素值取同一种符号 这个像素取不同的符号
sign. And we are basic computing in that way
而我们基本上都以此方式计算它的二阶导数
second derivatives. Just different implementations of this
这些是不同类型的计算二阶导数的方法
type of second derivative, derivatives. So what are the effects of this in an
那么在一幅图中 这会产生什么效果呢？
image? Very interesting.
很有趣
Here we see an image of the moon. What we see next in this image is the
这里是一幅月球的图像 接下来我们看到的就是这幅图像的拉普拉斯算子
laplacian It's the second derivative in the x direction, plus second derivative
就是x方向的二阶导数 加上y方向的二阶导数
in the y direction. And we actually see it implemented with
我们看到应用这个拉普拉斯算子后的效果
this. Here, we basically just stretch it.
我们将其加强
Remember, that we know how to modify histograms so we are stretching it.
记得我们已经知道如何修正直方图 类似于拉伸操作
And what we are doing next, is we are adding this to this.
接下来 我们把这个和它相叠加
So we basically take an image, takes the laplacian.
也就是我们有一幅图像 用拉普拉斯算子处理
We stretch it, and then we add them. And we get this image, which you can
将其强化后 然后将它们加起来 就得到了这幅图像
observe, is a bit sharper. Basically, some of the details are much
你能看到它被锐化了 基本上一些细节部分
more clear in this image than they were in this image.
在这幅图像中比之前的更为清晰
Now, we can actually make those details even more clear by computing a laplacian
现在我们能使这些细节更加清晰 通过计算不同的拉普拉斯算子
that takes in contrast with only a -4, a -8.
相比较于用 -4 这个值 这里用了-8
So it actually stretches the differences even more.
因此它能进一步对差异进行强化
The process would be the same. We take the image,
过程是一样的 我们拿这个图像
we compute the laplacian with this, at every pixel.
用此方法计算每个像素点的拉普拉斯算子
So every pixel is replaced by minus its own value, and plus the values of the
于是每个像素点都被它自身的负值与
surrounding pixels and then that we owe to the original image and look, we have a
周围像素点的正值之和取代 接着我们把它和原图片比较
very sharp rendering of these image, you see a lot of details here that were very
你看 我们得到了一个锐化的渲染效果 在这儿你能看到很多细节
blurry here. Very simple operation.
而原来这儿是很模糊的 这个操作很简单
Image plus its reflection gives us a very, very nice effect.
图像叠加上它的拉普拉斯算子 给我们带来了非常好的效果
Many, many of these combinations can be done.
有很多类似的组合可以达成目的
And here we see another example for a different image.
我们用另外的图片来试试
Again an image that looks a bit blurry. We see once again it's a laplacian.
又是一张看上去有点模糊的图片 这是它经拉普拉斯操作后的图像
It might be hard to notice. All what we have done from here to here
或许有点难看出是什么 我们所做的处理是
is once again to take second derivatives, and then we add them.
求了二阶导数并将它们相加
And look how much sharper this image is than this one.
看看这幅图像比之前的锐化了多少
Much, much sharper image. We can see a lot of the details that were
真的锐化了很多 我们能从中看到许多的细节
not very clear here. By a very simple operation of adding the
而之前不太清楚 通过简单地将原始图像
image to it's laplacian. And here, we see basically what's called
叠加到拉普拉斯处理后的图像上 这儿就是所谓的
a Sobel edges that are basically a different way of computing these
用于边缘检测的索贝尔算子 这是导数的另一种计算方式
derivatives. So, very interesting effects in images by
就像这样 会产生很有趣的效果
combining derivatives with the image in different directions.
图像与图像中不同方向上的导数相结合
Additions of derivatives, very, very interesting effects.
加上求导后的那个图所产生的效果 真的很有趣
One of those effects is what's called, Unsharp masking.
在这些效果中 有一种效果被称作反锐化掩模 (unsharp masking)
It's a very, very famous concept. Very, very simple.
是一个很著名而又很简单的概念
It's call Unsharp masking. We have it here.
在这里也有反锐化掩模效果
The idea is very simple. You take the image and you smooth it out.
原理很简单 将图像平滑处理
For example, how can we smooth an image? We already know many ways of doing that.
比如 我们如何平滑一幅图像呢？ 我们已经知道了很多方法
One of them is by doing local averages. So that's the response to a mask which is
其中一种就是取局部均值 反映在掩模中
all 1s. And, you know, 1 / 9 just to basically
就是全部都为1 然后再用 1/9 进行归一化处理
normalize. We do that, and then we subtract the
这样处理后 我们将其减去
original, minus the blurry image. Now, what's the mask correspondent to the
原始图像 减去 模糊化的图像 那么原始图像对应的掩模是什么呢？
original image? Very simple.
很简单
A mask that does nothing, has a one here and a zero.
如果是不起任何作用的掩模 它这里为1 其余为0
And replace X. So originally match is this mask, blurry
其他地方也是1和0 所以原始图像对应这个掩模
matches this mask. We take the differences, so it's this
而模糊图像对应这个掩膜  我们取其差异
mask minus this. Would produce this.
所以是用这个掩模减去这个掩模 就得到了这个图
Remember signs. So, if I subtract from this, this, I will
注意符号 那么如果我从这个掩模中减去这个模糊图像掩模
get a zero in the middle. And I will get, basically I won't get a
中间得到0 这是我将得到的
zero if I normalize. But I will basically get eight ninth, if
那么如果做了归一化 就不会得到0 而将得到 8/9
I do the normalization by the positive number, and every place else I will get
在用正数进行归一化的情况下 并且
-1/9 a negative number. That's kind of a derivative, as we saw
其它处为-1/9 是负数 这是一种导数 和我们之前看的一样
before, kind of an implementation of derivatives, in the, horizontal and
水平方向和垂直方向结合在一起的 导数的实现方法
vertical direction combined. We take that result and we add it to the
我们将此结果和原图像相加
original image. And look what we have, we basically are
看看我们得到的
enhancing the bandwidth as we have seen in the previous examples that basically
实际上边界被强化了 和我们在之前的例子中所见的一样
things become sharper because what we managed to do with the blurring was
图像被锐化了 这是因为我们模糊化是通过
reduce the boundaries and then when we add that back we had sharper boundaries
削弱边界得到的 当我们将边界叠加回去后 就得到了更加锐化的边界
are very sharp image and that's what that's called Unsharp masking, a very
以及锐化的图像 这就是所谓的反锐化掩模
simple operation and very powerful as well.
一个虽简单但强大的操作
So I'm going to conclude this video. In actually the next video by showing you
我接下来总结下 实际上下一个视频
once again inside math lab how we play with these type of operations of
将在 MATLAB 中给你们演示我们如何进行这些操作
smoothing added images very simple operations that produce very interesting
怎样进行平滑处理 并叠加图像 很简单的操作
effects in our images. So see you in the next video with our
并能给我们的图像带来明显的效果 那么下个视频
math lab demonstration.
会有 MATLAB 演示 再见 // 果壳教育无边界字幕组 | Coowesome | Mosesdc | 小白_远游